





Al Specialist for Health Sciences

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

I am a specialist in machine learning, with a focus on Health Sciences. I possess extensive experience in multidisciplinary scientific programming, research, and education. My primary expertise lies in the analysis of biological data using machine learning, mathematical optimization, and software development for multiple therapeutic areas. With effective communication skills and a passion for my field, I can articulate scientific concepts clearly and concisely to various audiences.



Python Matlab Java Git LATEX

EXPERIENCE

2023-Present Principal Investigator

University of Guadalajara

Supervising three thesis projects for the Master's in Bioengineering and Intelligent Computing | Working on personalised medicine development using Artificial Intelligence | Teaching classes on metabolic engineering | Conducting research seminars.

Machine Learning / Biological Data Analysis / Supervision / Research

2022-Present Consultant

Specialising in providing Artificial Intelligence and genome-scale modelling solutions to optimize processes and make strategic decisions | Collaborating with multidisciplinary teams to implement innovative solutions.

Machine Learning / Biological Data Analysis / Software Development / Python / Matlab

2018-2022 Researcher

Leiden University

Leading projects using omics data and artificial intelligence to create genomic-scale models of dopaminergic neurons derived from induced pluripotent stem cells to understand Parkinson's disease | Research cited in 1,402 peer-reviewed articles as measured by Google Scholar | Developer of the Constraint-Based Reconstruction and Analysis Toolbox for MATLAB (COBRA Toolbox) | Developed functions for multidimensional data integration | Presented findings at national and international professional conferences and meetings | Participated in international courses as a speaker.

Biological Data Analysis / Software Development / Machine Learning / Mathematical Optimization / Python / Matlab

EDUCATION

2018-2022 Ph.D. in Mathematics and Natural Sciences Leiden University, Netherlands

Thesis: Integration of omics data with genomic-scale modeling of dopaminergic neuronal

metabolism.

2014-2016 Master's in Integrated Systems Biology University of Luxembourg, Luxembourg

2007-2012 Biomedical Engineering University of Guadalajara, Mexico

PUBLICATIONS

In progress

Luojiao Huang, German Preciat, Jesus Alarcon-Gil. **fluxTrAM: Integration of tracer-based metabolomics data into atomically-resolved genome-scale metabolic networks for metabolic flux analysis.**

Under consideration

German Preciat, Agnieszka B Wegrzyn, Edinson Lucumi Moreno, et al. **Mechanistic model-driven exometabolomic characterisation of human dopaminergic neuronal metabolism**. $Nat\ Commun$.

Under editorial con-

sideration German Preciat, Agnieszka Wegrzyn, Ines Thiele, Thomas Hankemeier, Ronan Fleming, Xomic-

sToModel: Multiomics data integration and generation of thermodynamically consistent

metabolic models. Nat Protoc.

2023

Almut Heinken, Geeta Acharya, Dmitry Ravcheev, Johannes Hertel, Malgorzata Nyga, Onyedika Emmanuel Okpala, Marcus Hogan, Stefanía Magnúsdóttir, Filippo Martinelli, German Preciat, et al. **Genome-scale metabolic reconstruction of 7,302 human microorganisms for personalized medicine**. *Nat Biotechnol*.

2022

Ines Thiele, German Preciat y Ronan M.T. Fleming, **MetaboAnnotator: an efficient toolbox to annotate metabolites in genome-scale metabolic reconstructions**. *J Bioinform*.

2019

Laurent Heirendt, Sylvain Arreckx, Thomas Pfau, Sebastian N. Mendoza, Anne Richelle, Almut Heinken, Hulda S. Haraldsdóttir, Sarah M. Keating, Vanja Vlasov, Jacek Wachowiak, Stefania Magnusdottir, Chiam Yu Ng, German Preciat, et al. **Creation and analysis of biochemical constraint-based models:the COBRA Toolbox v3.0**. *Nat Protoc.*

2019

Miguel Oliveira, Silvain Arreckx, Donato Di Monte, German Preciat, Ayse Ulusoy y Ronan Fleming. The connectome is necessary but not sufficient for the spread of alpha-synuclein pathology in rats. bioRxiv.

2019

Alberto Noronha, Jennifer Modamio, Yohan Jarosz, Elisabeth Guerard, Nicolas Sompairac, German Preciat, et al. The Virtual Metabolic Human database: integrating human and gut microbiome metabolism with nutrition and disease. $Nucleic\ Acids\ Res$.

2018

Elizabeth Brunk, Swagatika Sahoo, Daniel C. Zielinski, Ali Altunkaya, Andreas Dräger, Nathan Mih, Andreas Prlić, Anand Sastry, German Preciat, et al. **Recon 3D: A Three-Dimensional View of Human Metabolism and Disease**. *Nature Biotechnol*.

2017

German Preciat, Lemmer El Assal, Alberto Noronha, Ines Thiele, Hulda S. Haraldsdóttir y Ronan M.T. Fleming. Comparative evaluation of atom mapping algorithms for balanced metabolic reactions: application to Recon 3D. *J Cheminform*.

ORAL PRESENTATIONS

2019 Metabolic Pathway Analysis (MPA) Riga, Latvia

Conserved moieties for genome-scale metabolic network reconstructions; Application in human dopaminergic neuronal metabolism.

2019 Recent Developments in Mathematical and Computational Biomedicine Oaxaca, Mexico

Atomically resolved metabolic network and constraint-based modeling in Parkinson's disease.

2018 18th International Study Group for Systems Biology (ISGSB) Conference Tromsø, Norway

Mechanistic model-driven exometabolomic characterization of human dopaminergic neuronal

metabolism.

2018 13th Pharmacometrics Network Benelux (PNB) Meeting Breda, Netherlands

Mechanistic model-driven exometabolomic characterization of human dopaminergic neuronal

metabolism.

Somatosensory and Motor Systems in Petri Neural Networks.

POSTER PRESENTATIONS

2017 OpenMultiMed Cost Training School in Systems Bioinformatics Nicosia, Cyprus

Exometabolomic predictions from an iHNESC derived DN in silico model.

2017 Metabolic Pathway Analysis (MPA) Bozeman, United States

Decomposition of the mitochondrial metabolic network based on atom mapping data.

2017 Department of Energy (DOE) Washington, United States

Comparison of atom mapping algorithms for metabolic reactions: application to Recon 3D.

2012 Annual Congress of Science and Technology Jalisco, Mexico

Dynamic model of neuroanatomical connections based on Petri neural networks.

2012 Annual Congress of Science and Technology Jalisco, Mexico

Vulnerable Hippocampal Region to Alzheimer's: Relationship with Acetylcholine and Gliosis in the

Triple Transgenic Model (3xTg-AD).

COURSES TAUGHT

2023-Present University of Guadalajara Jalisco, Mexico

Metabolic Engineering.

2022-Present University of Guadalajara Jalisco, Mexico

Research Seminar.

2021 Leiden University Leiden, Netherlands

ELIXIR Fluxomics Training School.

2019 Leiden University Leiden, Netherlands

BioSB Course Constraint-based modelling: introduction and advanced topics.

AWARDS

2018 The Cyprus Institute of Neurology & Genetics Nicosia, Cyprus

3rd place in best poster presentation.

2016 University of Luxembourg Luxembourg City, Luxembourg

Merit scholarship.

2014 University of Guadalajara Jalisco, Mexico

Scholarship for Master's studies.

LANGUAGES CERTIFICATES HOBBIES

Spanish - native English - advanced French - fluent

Luxembourgish - basic

Management Skills 2023

I love traveling the world and learning new languages. I also enjoy creating useful software for my daily

life, such as managing my investments or analysing helpful data.